<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>linux on ilManzo's blog</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/categories/linux/</link><description>Recent content in linux on ilManzo's blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2012-2023 Andrea Manzini</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ilmanzo.github.io/categories/linux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>debugging a problematic build</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/inspect-obs-vm-during-build/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/inspect-obs-vm-during-build/</guid><description>&lt;p>Today it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pi_Day">PI Day&lt;/a>, and among other activities I decided to submit an openSUSE package update for the &lt;a href="https://nim-lang.org/">nim compiler&lt;/a>.
It went almost all well but unfortunately I faced a problem: on the i586 platform it fails to build.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>linux resource control with cgroups</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/linux-resource-control-with-cgroups/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/linux-resource-control-with-cgroups/</guid><description>intro Resource isolation is an hot topic these days, and it&amp;rsquo;s a problem excellently solved by containerization. However, we can achieve isolation between internal tasks of an operating system by leveraging a technology exposed by the kernel: cgroups. This component is also used by Docker, and other Linux container technologies.
Cgroups are the Linux way of organizing groups of processes: roughly speaking a cgroup is to a process what a process is to a thread: one can have many threads belonging to the same process, and in the same way one can join many processes inside the same cgroup.</description></item><item><title>Hijack C library functions in D</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/hijack-c-library-function-in-d/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/hijack-c-library-function-in-d/</guid><description>I like playing with the D programming language and I wrote this little post to show how it&amp;rsquo;s easy to create a dynamic library (shared object, .so) that can be invoked in other programs; to have a little fun we will write a D replacement for the rand() C standard library function call. For your convenience, all the code is also on github
Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the demo implementation, a C program that calls 10 times the stdlib function rand() to get a random number.</description></item><item><title>a very simple NTP client in D</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/a-simple-ntp-client-in-d/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/a-simple-ntp-client-in-d/</guid><description>I am quite a fan of the D programming language and I think it deserves more attention, even if since a few months it&amp;rsquo;s becoming more and more popular, as it gained top20 in the TIOBE Index for February 2020.
As an experiment in network programming, I took this simple NTP client written in C and translated to D ; in my opinion while it&amp;rsquo;s keeping the low-level nature, it&amp;rsquo;s shorter, clearer and more effective.</description></item><item><title>linux: how to access DHCP options from client</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/access-dhcp-options-from-client/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/access-dhcp-options-from-client/</guid><description>As you may know, you can configure any DHCP server to send many options to the clients; for example to setup dns domains, http proxy (WPAD) and so on.
If you need to access these options from a linux client, you must configure the client to ASK the server for the new options, by editing /etc/dhcp/dhclient.conf, and add an entry like:
option WPAD code 252 = string; also request WPAD; done that, when you&amp;rsquo;ll ask for a dhcp, the dhclient process will invoke your hook scripts with two new environment variables, old_WPAD and new_WPAD, with the values before and after the renewal.</description></item><item><title>simple and easy linux job queue</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/simple-easy-job-queue-linux/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/simple-easy-job-queue-linux/</guid><description>Recently I have been in a situation where I needed a simple &amp;lsquo;batch&amp;rsquo; job scheduler, where I could submit some long-running tasks to a server and have a &amp;lsquo;system&amp;rsquo; that serialize access the execution with some basic job control facilities (remove a job from the queue, stop the processing, and so on).
Linux printing subsystem is already designed to do this, and we can exploit the CUPS printing subsystem to run our &amp;ldquo;batch&amp;rdquo; jobs.</description></item><item><title>redirect output of an already running process</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/redirect-output-of-running-process/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/redirect-output-of-running-process/</guid><description>Long story short: you have launched your script/program but forgot to redirect the output to a file for later inspection.
#!/usr/bin/python3 #sample endless running program that prints to stdout import time,datetime while True: print(datetime.datetime.now().time()) time.sleep(1) Using GNU Debugger you can re-attach to the process, then invoke the creation of a logfile and duplicate the file descriptor to make the system send the data to the new file, instead of the terminal:</description></item><item><title>Linux Day 2012</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/linux-day-2012/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/linux-day-2012/</guid><description>Anche quest&amp;rsquo;anno ho avuto il piacere di partecipare al Linux Day, organizzato per Verona presso la sede del LUG Verona in via dei Gelsi a Montorio; Ho tenuto una breve presentazione su un argomento che mi sta a cuore: partecipare attivamente alla comunita&amp;rsquo; del software libero, perche&amp;rsquo; anche se ormai Linux e Il free software hanno una discreta diffusione, la maggior parte degli utenti si limita all&amp;rsquo;utilizzo passivo e anzi spesso si lamenta per la scarsa qualita&amp;rsquo; del software open.</description></item></channel></rss>