<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on ilManzo's blog</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on ilManzo's blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 Andrea Manzini</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>automate OTP credentials for multi-factor authentication</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/otp-generation-from-command-line/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/otp-generation-from-command-line/</guid><description>Background: I work with one or more terminal command-line always opened and having to pick up my phone to generate an OTP breaks my flow; also it&amp;rsquo;s always nice to have an alternate source of multi-factor authentication if something bad happens, one day you could lose or break your trusty mobile device.
Therefore I was looking for a way to login through Okta portals without a phone. You may argument that this defeats the whole meaning of MFA, but let&amp;rsquo;s say it&amp;rsquo;s only an hack for research and fun purpose &amp;hellip;</description></item><item><title>linux resource control with cgroups</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/linux-resource-control-with-cgroups/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/linux-resource-control-with-cgroups/</guid><description>intro Resource isolation is an hot topic these days, and it&amp;rsquo;s a problem excellently solved by containerization. However, we can achieve isolation between internal tasks of an operating system by leveraging a technology exposed by the kernel: cgroups. This component is also used by Docker, and other Linux container technologies.
Cgroups are the Linux way of organizing groups of processes: roughly speaking a cgroup is to a process what a process is to a thread: one can have many threads belonging to the same process, and in the same way one can join many processes inside the same cgroup.</description></item><item><title>integration between Python and Rust - Part 2</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/writing-python-modules-in-rust-2/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/writing-python-modules-in-rust-2/</guid><description>In this post we are going to write a new module for python: a very simple function exported from Rust that we can consume in the Python interpreter. We&amp;rsquo;ll leverage the PyO3 Rust bindings for the Python interpreter.
Let&amp;rsquo;s start with a new Cargo project:
$ cargo init --lib demo_rust_lib and insert the required settings in Cargo.toml:
[package] name = &amp;#34;rusty&amp;#34; version = &amp;#34;0.1.0&amp;#34; edition = &amp;#34;2021&amp;#34; [lib] name=&amp;#34;rusty&amp;#34; crate-type = [&amp;#34;cdylib&amp;#34;] [dependencies.</description></item><item><title>integration between Python and Rust - Part 1</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/writing-python-modules-in-rust-1/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/writing-python-modules-in-rust-1/</guid><description>Let&amp;rsquo;s get our feet wet; in this first part I&amp;rsquo;ll write about a very simple way to interface Rust and Python. First of all let&amp;rsquo;s build a Rust dynamic library with some basic functions.
// this file is: src/lib.rs #[no_mangle] pub extern &amp;#34;C&amp;#34; fn hello() { println!(&amp;#34;Hello from the library!&amp;#34;); } #[no_mangle] pub extern &amp;#34;C&amp;#34; fn sum(a: i32, b: i32) -&amp;gt; i32 { a + b } your Cargo.toml should look like this:</description></item><item><title>playing with eBPF interface - 2</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/tracing-with-ebpf-02/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/tracing-with-ebpf-02/</guid><description>In the last post we introduced the BCC framework to interface Python code with eBPF facility. Now we are ready to make one step further!
#!/usr/bin/python3 import bcc bpf = bcc.BPF(text=&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&amp;#34; #include &amp;lt;uapi/linux/ptrace.h&amp;gt; int trace_malloc(struct pt_regs *ctx, size_t size) { bpf_trace_printk(&amp;#34;size=%d\\n&amp;#34;,size); return 0; };&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&amp;#34;) bpf.attach_uprobe(name=&amp;#34;c&amp;#34;,sym=&amp;#34;malloc&amp;#34;,fn_name=&amp;#34;trace_malloc&amp;#34;) while 1: (task, pid, cpu, flags, ts, msg) = bpf.trace_fields() print(f&amp;#34;task={task}\tmsg={msg}&amp;#34;) This code is a little more complex, but still quite easy: first of all we use bcc to attach an &amp;ldquo;user space probe&amp;rdquo; instead of a kernel probe, and the function being observed will be libc&amp;rsquo;s malloc.</description></item><item><title>playing with eBPF interface</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/playing-with-ebpf-01/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/playing-with-ebpf-01/</guid><description>eBPF is a revolutionary technology that can run sandboxed programs in the Linux kernel without changing kernel source code or loading kernel modules. Basically any user can write code for a virtual machine that can interact with the kernel data structure and functions.
bcc is an high-level helper interface to eBPF (another is bpftrace). To use it, start by following installation guide , but if you have a recent Debian system, it&amp;rsquo;s just a matter of installing some packages:</description></item><item><title>a 'pythonic' fileinput module for the D programming language</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/fileinput-for-d-programming-language/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/fileinput-for-d-programming-language/</guid><description>When I write small command line utilities in Python, I often take advantage of the fileinput module that makes working with text files very convenient: the library permits to write quickly and easily a loop over standard input or a list of files, something like perl -a or awk line processing.
Then the size of input data grew, and also for a language comparison, I wanted to port my utility in the D programming language, but I cannot find an equivalent module, so I decided to write one myself.</description></item><item><title>Writing Python modules in Nim</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/writing-python-modules-in-nim/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/writing-python-modules-in-nim/</guid><description>Nim is a statically typed compiled systems programming language. It combines successful concepts from mature languages like Python, Ada and Modula. It&amp;rsquo;s Efficient, expressive, elegant and definitely worth to check.
While I was playing with it, I stumbled upon an interesting module that allows almost seamless interoperability betweeen Nim and Python; so I&amp;rsquo;m building a small proof of concept on this github project.
first of all the Nim code: # file: demo.</description></item><item><title>A new project to learn the Crystal Programming Language</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/a-new-project-to-learn-the-crystal-programming-language/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/a-new-project-to-learn-the-crystal-programming-language/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve started a new side project named Crystal Koans, it&amp;rsquo;s a simple series of exercises organized as a big unit test suite.
The &amp;ldquo;koans&amp;rdquo; are heavily inspired by similar projects for other languages, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t found anything similar for Crystal. The project has been included in the awesome collection under the official Learning Resource for the language.
I&amp;rsquo;ll try to maintain and evolve it in the spare time, I hope you&amp;rsquo;ll find it useful, and any form of contribution is welcome.</description></item><item><title>Hijack C library functions in D</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/hijack-c-library-function-in-d/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/hijack-c-library-function-in-d/</guid><description>I like playing with the D programming language and I wrote this little post to show how it&amp;rsquo;s easy to create a dynamic library (shared object, .so) that can be invoked in other programs; to have a little fun we will write a D replacement for the rand() C standard library function call. For your convenience, all the code is also on github
Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the demo implementation, a C program that calls 10 times the stdlib function rand() to get a random number.</description></item><item><title>a very simple NTP client in D</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/a-simple-ntp-client-in-d/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/a-simple-ntp-client-in-d/</guid><description>I am quite a fan of the D programming language and I think it deserves more attention, even if since a few months it&amp;rsquo;s becoming more and more popular, as it gained top20 in the TIOBE Index for February 2020.
As an experiment in network programming, I took this simple NTP client written in C and translated to D ; in my opinion while it&amp;rsquo;s keeping the low-level nature, it&amp;rsquo;s shorter, clearer and more effective.</description></item><item><title>migrating a repository from mercurial to git</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/migrating-a-repository-from-mercurial-to-git/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/migrating-a-repository-from-mercurial-to-git/</guid><description>Since bitbucket is sunsetting the support for mercurial repositories, I wrote a quick and dirty script to automate the migration from mercurial to GIT:
#!/bin/bash set -e set -u if [ &amp;#34;$#&amp;#34; -ne 3 ]; then echo &amp;#34;Illegal number of parameters&amp;#34; echo &amp;#34;usage: migrate.sh reponame hgrepourl gitrepourl&amp;#34; exit 1 fi REPONAME=$1 HGURL=$2 GITURL=$3 echo &amp;#34;Migrating $REPONAME from $HGURL to $GITURL...&amp;#34; cd /tmp hg clone $HGURL cd $REPONAME hg bookmark -r default master hg bookmarks hg cd .</description></item><item><title>il linguaggio Lua: parte 14</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-14/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-14/</guid><description>segue dalla parte 13
Coroutine Come approccio alla programmazione concorrente, il linguaggio Lua non ha meccanismi interni per gestire nativamente i thread, ma si può appoggiare a ciò che offre il sistema operativo sottostante. Lua invece internamente offre il supporto alle coroutine: un programma Lua può avere diversi percorsi di esecuzione &amp;lsquo;parallela&amp;rsquo; ognuno col proprio stack e variabili locali ma che condividono risorse e variabili globali con le altre coroutine.</description></item><item><title>il linguaggio Lua: parte 13</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-13/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-13/</guid><description>segue dalla parte 12
Upvalue e Closure Per chi non ha familiarità con i concetti di programmazione funzionale questi termini possono sembrare un po’ oscuri; vediamo di chiarirli con un semplice esempio:
-- definisco una funzione che parte da un numero N e conta alla rovescia function CreaContatore(N) local v=N local function conta(x) if v&amp;gt;=x then v=v-x end return v end return conta end -- creo qualche istanza: contaDaDieci=CreaContatore(10) contaDaCento=CreaContatore(100) print(contaDaDieci(1)) 9 print(contaDaCento(1)) 99 print(contaDaCento(1)) 98 print(contaDaDieci(1)) 8 print(contaDaDieci(2)) 6 print(contaDaCento(10)) 88 osserviamo le variabili N,v che usate dalla funzione interna: non sono locali, ma nemmeno globali&amp;hellip; Sono upvalue, ovvero riferimenti che provengono da uno stackframe esterno.</description></item><item><title>il linguaggio Lua: parte 12</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-12/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-12/</guid><description>segue dalla parte 11
segnalazioni lunari Tra le rocks più interessanti citiamo quelle che permettono le operazioni di networking, come luasocket; salendo di livello, spicca il Kepler project, che comprende un intero stack per applicazioni web: Lapis micro framework, il framework MVC Sailor, e TurboLua, un tool per costuire velocissimi microservizi REST .
Concludiamo la panoramica sulle librerie accennando ai moduli per creare interfacce grafiche; al pari degli altri linguaggi di scripting, Lua offre binding per i maggiori toolkit grafici: curses, GTK, QT, fltk, wx si usano come negli altri linguaggi e sarebbe qui tedioso illustrarne le modalità.</description></item><item><title>il linguaggio Lua: parte 11</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-11/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-11/</guid><description>segue dalla parte 10
Rocce di Luna Poter organizzare il codice in più file è molto utile per modularizzare i programmi, creando package che verranno caricati tramite l&amp;rsquo;istruzione require “nomefile”. Vediamo un esempio:
-- geompkg.lua module(&amp;#34;geom&amp;#34;) local function quadrato(x) return x*x end local function rettangolo(b,h) return b*h end function area(param) if param.lato then return quadrato(param.lato) end local area=rettangolo(param.base,param.altezza) if param.triangolo or param.trapezio then return area/2 end return area end -- usepkg.</description></item><item><title>il linguaggio Lua: parte 10</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-10/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-10/</guid><description>segue dalla parte 9
stringhe e regular expression in questa puntata apriremo una piccola digressione per analizzare le funzionalità del modulo string, in particolare l&amp;rsquo;uso delle regular expression.
Il modulo string ci mette a disposizione potenti funzioni di ricerca e sostituzione basate su espressioni regolari. Una completa implementazione delle regexp POSIX occuperebbe più dell&amp;rsquo;intero linguaggio, ma tutto sommato le funzionalità principali sono state mantenute, e gli autori di Lua sono riusciti a impacchettare un “motore” di pattern matching in meno di 500 righe di codice.</description></item><item><title>a honeypot ssh server in Go</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/a-honeypot-ssh-server-in-go/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/a-honeypot-ssh-server-in-go/</guid><description>honey-ssh-pot Curious about who and how attempts ssh login to your home server ? Me too&amp;hellip; So I wrote a very simple ssh honeypot, just to collect interesting info about the kind guys who knocks my door :)
warning: this is safe, but don&amp;rsquo;t run the service (well, ANY service) as root user. Even better if you can run it as a dedicate unprivileged user.
This program is only for didactic use and not intended for deployment in a production network environment.</description></item><item><title>il linguaggio Lua: parte 9</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-09/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-09/</guid><description>segue dalla parte 8
il modulo lunare Per mantenere la sua natura minimalista, Lua ha ben poche funzionalità incluse nel linguaggio e delega molti aspetti a librerie e moduli esterni. Ad esempio le operazioni matematiche sono accessibili nel package, o se preferite, namespace col prefisso math:
$ lua &amp;gt;print(math.sin(math.pi/2)) 1 sarebbe oltremodo noioso elencare tutte le funzioni presenti, basti dire che oltre alle funzioni trigonometriche abbiamo logaritmi, esponenziali, modulo, minimo, massimo, arrotondamenti e generazione di valori random.</description></item><item><title>il linguaggio Lua: ottava parte</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-08/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-08/</guid><description>segue dalla settima parte
Oggetti volanti e non Lua non è un linguaggio nativamente object-oriented. Se nei nostri script volessimo adottare uno stile OOP, ad esempio per modellare le operazioni su un conto corrente la cosa più naturale sarebbe usare una tabella:
Conto = { saldo = 200.0 } Questa sintassi potrebbe essere assimilata al &amp;lsquo;costruttore&amp;rsquo; dell&amp;rsquo;oggetto Conto. Possiamo anche definire dei metodi:
function Conto.preleva(cifra) Conto.saldo = Conto.saldo - cifra end e quindi potremmo comodamente chiamare, problemi economici a parte:</description></item><item><title>il linguaggio Lua: settima parte</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-07/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-07/</guid><description>segue dalla sesta parte
Iteratori e lua funzionale Cos&amp;rsquo;è un iteratore? Informaticamente parlando, è un costrutto che ci permette di scorrere strutture dati come liste, array, elenchi. In pratica, dato un elemento della struttura il compito dell&amp;rsquo;iteratore è farci avere il prossimo su cui operare. Non ci stupirà apprendere che in Lua gli iteratori sono funzioni. Vediamo un semplice esempio:
function reverse_iter(t) local i=#t+1 return function() i=i-1 if i&amp;gt;=0 then return t[i] end end end reverse_iter è una fabbrica (factory) di funzioni: ogni volta che la chiamiamo, ci crea una nuova closure, ossia l&amp;rsquo;iteratore specifico per l&amp;rsquo;array che gli passiamo.</description></item><item><title>a simple PNG decoder in Go</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/a-simple-png-decoder/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/a-simple-png-decoder/</guid><description>while working with image files, I needed a simple way to analyze content of a picture; so I wrote this tool that &amp;ldquo;walks&amp;rdquo; inside a PNG file and reports all the chunks seen; this is intended to be expanded with more features in a future.
package main import ( &amp;#34;encoding/binary&amp;#34; &amp;#34;fmt&amp;#34; &amp;#34;io&amp;#34; &amp;#34;os&amp;#34; ) type chunk struct { Length uint32 ChunkType [4]byte } func main() { if len(os.Args) != 2 { fmt.</description></item><item><title>il linguaggio Lua: sesta parte</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-06/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-06/</guid><description>segue dalla quinta parte
Quando il saggio indica la luna, lo sciocco guarda il dito Nello scorse puntate abbiamo appreso le basi di un linguaggio minimalista, il cui motto è “doing more with less”, che occupa meno byte della vostra foto su Facebook e che i benchmark dichiarano il più veloce tra i linguaggi di scripting. Nato da menti brasiliane, l&amp;rsquo;hanno chiamato Lua, che vuol dire Luna in portoghese. Lua viene usato come linguaggio di scripting in Angry Birds, World of Warcraft e decine di altri videogame e software: nello scorso post abbiamo visto come creare un semplice plugin per VLC.</description></item><item><title>linux: how to access DHCP options from client</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/access-dhcp-options-from-client/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/access-dhcp-options-from-client/</guid><description>As you may know, you can configure any DHCP server to send many options to the clients; for example to setup dns domains, http proxy (WPAD) and so on.
If you need to access these options from a linux client, you must configure the client to ASK the server for the new options, by editing /etc/dhcp/dhclient.conf, and add an entry like:
option WPAD code 252 = string; also request WPAD; done that, when you&amp;rsquo;ll ask for a dhcp, the dhclient process will invoke your hook scripts with two new environment variables, old_WPAD and new_WPAD, with the values before and after the renewal.</description></item><item><title>il linguaggio Lua: quinta parte</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-05/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-05/</guid><description>segue dalla quarta parte
“Sonata al chiaro di luna” : un plugin per vlc Come dicevamo all&amp;rsquo;inizio, Lua è usato da numerose applicazioni come linguaggio di estensione; per scopi didattici ho scelto di scrivere un semplice plugin per un programma diffuso, il media player universale VLC. Con questo plugin risolveremo per sempre l&amp;rsquo;annoso problema di decidere cosa sarebbe meglio sgranocchiare durante la visione! L&amp;rsquo;integrazione con lo scripting Lua è documentata in una serie di file README.</description></item><item><title>il linguaggio Lua: parte 4</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-04/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-04/</guid><description>segue dalla terza parte
“Moonlight Bay” (ovvero: “chiedi chi erano i vectors”) L&amp;rsquo;unica struttura dati disponibile in Lua è rappresentata dagli array o meglio, dalle tabelle (o hash): array associativi formati da coppie chiave-valore, nelle quali sia la chiave sia il valore possono essere qualsiasi tipo di dato. Vediamo un paio di esempi, dapprima un normale vettore:
&amp;gt; i = 3 &amp;gt; a = {1,3,5,7,9} &amp;gt; print(i,a[3],a[4],a[i+3]) questa sequenza stampa i valori 3,5,7,nil; la prima cosa che appare diversa rispetto ad un altro linguaggio è che gli indici per gli array partono da 1 anziché da zero; la seconda è che un eventuale sforamento dell&amp;rsquo;array non causa errore ma semplicemente ritorna nil.</description></item><item><title>il linguaggio Lua: parte 3</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-03/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-03/</guid><description>segue dalla seconda parte
Che fai tu luna in ciel ? : le funzioni Fino a che scriviamo script di poche righe, possiamo inserire le istruzioni nel programma principale, ma aumentando la complessità diventa necessario organizzare il codice in pezzi indipendenti e riutilizzabili; come in tutti gli altri linguaggi, in Lua è possibile definire funzioni; vediamo un esempio piuttosto classico:
function fattoriale(n) local f=1 -- variabile locale alla funzione for i=2,n do f=f*i end return f Abbiamo definito la funzione fattoriale, che da ora in avanti possiamo richiamare nel nostro codice:</description></item><item><title>convert a binary file to ascii using hexdump</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/hexdump-for-binary-file-manipulation/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/hexdump-for-binary-file-manipulation/</guid><description>I have a binary file with data stored as two-byte big-endian 16-bit words. We need to extract the values in the file and print them in decimal ASCII format, so to obtain numbers in the 0-655535 range.
let&amp;rsquo;s create the sample file:
$ echo -en &amp;#34;\x01\x02\x03\x04\x05\x06\x07\x08&amp;#34; &amp;gt; file.bin and show its content in binary form:
$ hexdump -C file.bin 00000000 01 02 03 04 05 06 07 08 |........| 00000008 to get the desired output we can use the powerful, but little documented format string option of hexdump:</description></item><item><title>playing with Crystal Programming Language</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/playing-with-crystal-programming-language/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/playing-with-crystal-programming-language/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve started experimenting with the Crystal Programming Language. It&amp;rsquo;s a nice and clean language with syntax similar to Ruby, but compiled to fast native code, and a lot of clever ideas, like union types and seamless C integration The project is still in early stages, but it&amp;rsquo;s promising.
Just to see how easy, I ported a small python library to Crystal, you can find it on https://github.com/ilmanzo/spark. I hope to find the time to improve on it!</description></item><item><title>a simple HTTP rewriting proxy</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/a-simple-http-rewriting-proxy/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/a-simple-http-rewriting-proxy/</guid><description>This is an example of using goproxy, a fast and robust multithread proxy engine to develop an HTTP proxy that rewrites content on the fly, with multiple search and substitutions. It can be useful for debugging and other less noble (but useful) purposes &amp;hellip;
// rewriting_proxy project main.go package main import ( &amp;#34;bytes&amp;#34; &amp;#34;flag&amp;#34; &amp;#34;io/ioutil&amp;#34; &amp;#34;log&amp;#34; &amp;#34;net/http&amp;#34; &amp;#34;github.com/elazarl/goproxy&amp;#34; ) var replacements = []struct { from []byte to []byte }{ {[]byte(&amp;#34;#e8ecec&amp;#34;), []byte(&amp;#34;Red&amp;#34;)}, // ugly colors!</description></item><item><title>wrapping c plus plus classes in Python</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/wrapping-c-plus-plus-classes-in-python/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/wrapping-c-plus-plus-classes-in-python/</guid><description>This is a quick and dirty way to interface C++ code with Python, translating one or more C++ classes in Python objects.
First, we need some c++ sample code:
//myclass.h #ifndef MYCLASS_H #define MYCLASS_H #include &amp;lt;string&amp;gt; using namespace std; namespace pets { class Dog { public: Dog(string name, int age); virtual ~Dog(); string talk(); protected: string m_name; int m_age; }; } //myclass.cpp #include &amp;#34;myclass.h&amp;#34; #include &amp;lt;string&amp;gt; namespace pets { Dog::Dog(std::string name, int age): m_name(name),m_age(age) { } Dog::~Dog() { } std::string Dog::talk() { return &amp;#34;BARK!</description></item><item><title>il linguaggio Lua: parte 2</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-02/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-02/</guid><description>segue dalla prima parte
Moonwalking: Tipi di dato Nello scorsa puntata abbiamo utilizzato due degli otto tipi disponibili: i numeri e le stringhe. Per semplicita&amp;rsquo;, Lua non distingue tra interi e floating point: tutti i valori numerici sono conservati come double, cioe&amp;rsquo; in virgola mobile a doppia precisione. Nel caso la CPU non disponesse di unita&amp;rsquo; FPU, è possibile cambiare una riga nel sorgente (per l&amp;rsquo;esattezza, #define LUA_NUMBER in lua.h) e ricompilare; questo si fa tipicamente nei sistemi embedded con processori a basse prestazioni.</description></item><item><title>how to automatically expire mysql records after a fixed amount of time</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/automatic-expiring-of-mysql-rows/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/automatic-expiring-of-mysql-rows/</guid><description>the issue we have a database table containing usernames and passwords, but we want to make them temporary like expiring after a fixed number of days from the creation. This is typical usage for a wi-fi captive portal with RADIUS authentication backed on mysql.
the idea we store a new field in the table with the timestamp, and run a periodic &amp;ldquo;cleaner&amp;rdquo; job that deletes record older than X days.</description></item><item><title>il linguaggio Lua: prima parte</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-01/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/il-linguaggio-lua-01/</guid><description>introduzione Ho sempre avuto un debole per il software leggero e snello: sara&amp;rsquo; un retaggio di quando la memoria si misurava in Kb e lo storage era basato su&amp;hellip; audiocassette! Lua e&amp;rsquo; un linguaggio che incarna questa filosofia: occupa circa un centinaio di kbyte (meno di molte pagine web), ha una stupefacente rapidita&amp;rsquo; di esecuzione, una sintassi chiara e, come bonus, gira su qualsiasi CPU per cui sia disponibile un compilatore C.</description></item><item><title>monit helper for quota monitoring in go</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/golang-quota-monit-helper/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/golang-quota-monit-helper/</guid><description>I want to keep under control a system where each user has an amount of filesystem quota reserved; in particular I would like to get notified if and when a user exceeds some treshold. Since I already have Monit in place in the server, I took the chance to write a small Go utility in order to retrieve the quota percentage.
This is also an example on how to run external programs in Go and filter the output using regular expressions.</description></item><item><title>simple and easy linux job queue</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/simple-easy-job-queue-linux/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/simple-easy-job-queue-linux/</guid><description>Recently I have been in a situation where I needed a simple &amp;lsquo;batch&amp;rsquo; job scheduler, where I could submit some long-running tasks to a server and have a &amp;lsquo;system&amp;rsquo; that serialize access the execution with some basic job control facilities (remove a job from the queue, stop the processing, and so on).
Linux printing subsystem is already designed to do this, and we can exploit the CUPS printing subsystem to run our &amp;ldquo;batch&amp;rdquo; jobs.</description></item><item><title>serata introduttiva al FabLab sulla programmazione Python</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/serata-fablab/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/serata-fablab/</guid><description>Pubblico qui le slide che ho usato durante la serata dedicata alla programmazione Python, svoltasi presso il FabLab Verona
http://ilmanzo.github.io/files/slide_serata_python_fablab_2015.html</description></item><item><title>CGI with the Go Programming Language</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/cgi-apps-in-go/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/cgi-apps-in-go/</guid><description>Following with the GO standard library exploration, I&amp;rsquo;ve written a toy example for using the CGI features. Native GoLang CGI web applications are very fast and can be useful for example in embedded systems, or in cheap web hosting where is not possible to run custom HTTP servers. The solution has some weak points, starting from lock management, but is only presented as a proof of concept and not for real use cases.</description></item><item><title>sample template usage in the Go Programming Language</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/templating-in-go/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/templating-in-go/</guid><description>The GO programming language has a nice and useful standard library, which includes a powerful templating engine out of the box.
Here I wrote an example, generating HTML output from a simple data structure.
This program generates the following HTML output:
&amp;lt;!DOCTYPE html&amp;gt; &amp;lt;html&amp;gt;&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;my todo list&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt; &amp;lt;body&amp;gt;&amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;my TODO list&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt; &amp;lt;ul&amp;gt; &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; 1 Take out the dog &amp;lt;/li&amp;gt; &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; 2 Feed the cat &amp;lt;/li&amp;gt; &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; 3 Learn GO programming &amp;lt;/li&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/ul&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt; Next step: use the template to provide interactive web pages &amp;hellip;</description></item><item><title>redirect output of an already running process</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/redirect-output-of-running-process/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/redirect-output-of-running-process/</guid><description>Long story short: you have launched your script/program but forgot to redirect the output to a file for later inspection.
#!/usr/bin/python3 #sample endless running program that prints to stdout import time,datetime while True: print(datetime.datetime.now().time()) time.sleep(1) Using GNU Debugger you can re-attach to the process, then invoke the creation of a logfile and duplicate the file descriptor to make the system send the data to the new file, instead of the terminal:</description></item><item><title>Sincronizzare una directory tra due server linux</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/simple-directory-sync/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/simple-directory-sync/</guid><description>Obiettivo vogliamo mantenere la stessa directory sincronizzata su due server linux.
Questo significa che ogni aggiunta/rimozione/modifica di file in questa directory verrà automaticamente riportato sull&amp;rsquo;altro (salvo conflitti). Diamo per assunto che i due server siano raggiungibili via rete, ma per qualsiasi motivo non sia possibile collegare dello spazio disco condiviso.
Implementazione Per raggiungere lo scopo, utilizzeremo il tool: csync2
su entrambi i server (che chiameremo nodo1 e nodo2), installiamo i pacchetti necessari:</description></item><item><title>A new project to learn the D Programming Language</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/a-new-project-to-learn-the-d-programming-language/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/a-new-project-to-learn-the-d-programming-language/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve started a new side project named D Lang Koans, it&amp;rsquo;s a simple series of exercises organized in a unit test suite.
The &amp;ldquo;koans&amp;rdquo; are heavily inspired by similar projects for other languages, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t found anything similar for D.
I&amp;rsquo;ll try to maintain and evolve it in the spare time, I hope you&amp;rsquo;ll find it useful.</description></item><item><title>monitor apache performance statistics</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/logging-apache-performance-historical-statistics/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/logging-apache-performance-historical-statistics/</guid><description>the Apache module mod_status is very useful for inspecting your running webserver, but it gives you only realtime informations about workers, connections, and so on. I wanted a way to keep this data and then be able to do comparison, charts and more useful reports. The first step was configuring mod_status in order to be only accessible from localhost:
andrea@myserver:~$ cat /etc/apache2/mods-enabled/status.conf &amp;lt;IfModule mod_status.c&amp;gt; # # Allow server status reports generated by mod_status, # with the URL of http://servername/server-status # Uncomment and change the &amp;#34;192.</description></item><item><title>Linux: get simple I/O statistics per process</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/simple-io-statistics-per-process/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/simple-io-statistics-per-process/</guid><description>I had a trouble with a long process running and wish to know how much I/O this process is doing, so I wrote this quick and dirty python 2.x script:
import time,sys,datetime def read_stat(pid): f=open(&amp;#34;/proc/%s/io&amp;#34; % pid ,&amp;#34;r&amp;#34;) for line in f: if line.startswith(&amp;#39;rchar&amp;#39;): rchar=line.split(&amp;#39;:&amp;#39;)[1] continue if line.startswith(&amp;#39;wchar&amp;#39;): wchar=line.split(&amp;#39;:&amp;#39;)[1] continue f.close() return int(rchar),int(wchar) pid=sys.argv[1] r0,w0 = read_stat(pid) while 1: time.sleep(1) r1,w1 = read_stat(pid) print &amp;#34;%s\t\tr=%s\t\tw=%s&amp;#34; % (datetime.datetime.now().time(),r1-r0,w1-w0) r0,w0=r1,w1 You must give the process PID number as input to the script.</description></item><item><title>how to setup disk redundancy with BTRFS filesystem</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/btrfs-mirroring/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/btrfs-mirroring/</guid><description>Starting with a plain old one-disk configuration&amp;hellip;
# df -h Filesystem Size Used Avail Use% Mounted on /dev/sda2 5.8G 590M 5.0G 11% /data thanks to the power of btrfs, let&amp;rsquo;s add a second hard disk, with mirrored data AND without unmounting/reformatting! :) also note the different size&amp;hellip;.
# fdisk -l Disk /dev/sda: 6 GiB, 6442450944 bytes, 12582912 sectors Units: sectors of 1 * 512 = 512 bytes Sector size (logical/physical): 512 bytes / 512 bytes I/O size (minimum/optimal): 512 bytes / 512 bytes Disklabel type: dos Disk identifier: 0xea97ecdc Device Boot Start End Blocks Id System /dev/sda1 2048 526335 262144 82 Linux swap / Solaris /dev/sda2 * 526336 12582911 6028288 83 Linux Disk /dev/sdb: 4 GiB, 4294967296 bytes, 8388608 sectors Units: sectors of 1 * 512 = 512 bytes Sector size (logical/physical): 512 bytes / 512 bytes I/O size (minimum/optimal): 512 bytes / 512 bytes &amp;hellip; state of the filesystem before the change&amp;hellip;</description></item><item><title>Compress and encrypt your backups</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/compress-and-encrypt-your-remote-backups/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/compress-and-encrypt-your-remote-backups/</guid><description>It&amp;rsquo;s always recommended to backup your data for safety, but for safety AND security let&amp;rsquo;s encrypt your backups!
to compress and encrypt with &amp;lsquo;mypassword&amp;rsquo;: tar -Jcf - directory | openssl aes-256-cbc -salt -k mypassword -out backup.tar.xz.aes
to decrypt and decompress: openssl aes-256-cbc -d -salt -k mypassword -in backup.tar.xz.aes | tar -xJ -f - Another trick with the tar command is useful for remote backups: tar -zcvfp - /wwwdata | ssh root@remote.</description></item><item><title>how to display the IP address of a virtual machine before logon</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/know-your-vm-address-before-logon/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/know-your-vm-address-before-logon/</guid><description>For testing or development purposes, I do a wide use of small linux virtual machines.
After spawning a new guest (Virtualbox, VMWare or any other), often you want to log on over ssh but you don&amp;rsquo;t yet know its ip address. You need to login as &amp;lsquo;root&amp;rsquo; in the console just to issue a quick &amp;lsquo;ifconfig&amp;rsquo;, and after writing down the address, you logout and connect with your comfortable terminal. In order to save some time and keystrokes, I put this in my rc.</description></item><item><title>dovecot: cleaning old Spam and Trash messages after some days</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/postfix-dovecot-cleanup-virtual-folders/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/postfix-dovecot-cleanup-virtual-folders/</guid><description>This script is useful to delete old messages in &amp;ldquo;Junk&amp;rdquo; mail folders (Spam, Trash) automatically after some days.
adapted from these notes to work on debian/postfixadmin/dovecot
#!/bin/bash # # itera sulle mailbox cancellando messaggi vecchi # per default, nel cestino 30gg e Spam 15 gg # # MySQL details HOST=&amp;#34;127.0.0.1&amp;#34;; USER=&amp;#34;put_here_your_mysql_user&amp;#34;; PWD=&amp;#34;put_here_your_mysql_password&amp;#34;; MYSQL=&amp;#34;/usr/bin/mysql&amp;#34;; # dovecot details DOVEADM=&amp;#34;/usr/bin/doveadm&amp;#34;; TEMPFILE=$(/bin/mktemp) # Output sql to a file that we want to run echo &amp;#34;use postfixadmin; select username from mailbox&amp;#34; &amp;gt; $TEMPFILE # Run the query and get the results (adjust the path to mysql) results=$($MYSQL -h $HOST -u $USER -p$PWD -N &amp;lt; $TEMPFILE); # Loop through each row for row in $results do echo &amp;#34;Purging $row Trash and Junk mailbox.</description></item><item><title>number of physical sockets and cpu cores</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/sockets-and-cores/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/sockets-and-cores/</guid><description>a small script to check out the number of processors in your linux machine
#!/bin/bash S=$(grep "physical id" /proc/cpuinfo | sort -u | wc -l) C=$(grep "cpu cores" /proc/cpuinfo |sort -u |cut -d":" -f2) grep -i "model name" /proc/cpuinfo echo your system has $S sockets with $C CPU cores each mandatory sample output:
model name : Intel(R) Xeon(R) CPU L5640 @ 2.27GHz your system has 2 sockets with 6 CPU cores each</description></item><item><title>Automate Cisco ssh connections with plink in Windows</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/plink-automation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/plink-automation/</guid><description>A quick and dirty way to send a bunch of commands to any ssh device (in my case, Cisco appliances)&amp;hellip;
create a plain old batch file with commands echoed inside: @echo off echo ter len 0 echo show ver echo show clock echo exit execute the batch, piping its output to plink.exe (putty command link ssh client): c:\&amp;gt; commands.bat | plink -ssh -l username -pw password 11.22.33.44</description></item><item><title>semplice rate limit in Sinatra</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/semplice-rate-limit-in-sinatra/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/semplice-rate-limit-in-sinatra/</guid><description>Giocando con Sinatra ho avuto l&amp;rsquo;esigenza di servire una determinata pagina solo con un certa frequenza (tecnicamente un rate-limit); la cosa si puo&amp;rsquo; fare installando il middleware Rack:Throttle ma non volevo aggiungere un&amp;rsquo;altra gemma alle dipendenze&amp;hellip;
In questo esempio se al server arriva piu&amp;rsquo; di una richiesta in un intervallo di cinque secondi, rispondiamo a tono&amp;hellip;
SECONDS_BETWEEN_REQUEST=5 enable :sessions def ratelimit? now=Time.new.to_i session[&amp;#39;lastrequest&amp;#39;]||=0 #inizializza se non presente result=(now-session[&amp;#39;lastrequest&amp;#39;])&amp;lt;SECONDS_BETWEEN_REQUEST #passati dall&amp;#39;ultima richiesta ?</description></item><item><title>run-parts e problemi di crontab</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/run-parts-problemi-crontab/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/run-parts-problemi-crontab/</guid><description>Mi e&amp;rsquo; capitato di inserire degli script nelle varie directory /etc/cron.daily, /etc/cron.weekly ma di scoprire che questi script non vengono eseguiti. Il motivo e&amp;rsquo; che il run-parts usato nelle Debian e derivate ignora i file che contengono un &amp;ldquo;.&amp;rdquo; (e quindi tutti quelli con l&amp;rsquo;estensione)
Questo comportamento e&amp;rsquo; documentato anche nella man page, e previene alcuni inconvenienti come l&amp;rsquo;esecuzione dei .bak ma lo scrivo anche qui per ricordarmelo &amp;hellip; E forse potra&amp;rsquo; essere utile a qualcun altro :)</description></item><item><title>generare comandi di creazione utenze a partire da un passwd</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/generare-comandi-di-creazione-utenze-a-partire-da-un-passwd/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/generare-comandi-di-creazione-utenze-a-partire-da-un-passwd/</guid><description>A volte e&amp;rsquo; necessario replicare le utenze con gli stessi parametri su piu&amp;rsquo; server linux diversi.
Perche&amp;rsquo; farlo a mano ? Se sono tanti e&amp;rsquo; un lavoro noioso e potremmo anche commettere degli errori.
Ecco un semplice one-liner che fa il parsing di un file /etc/passwd e genera i corrispondenti comandi useradd
awk -F: '{printf &amp;quot;useradd -m -u%s -g%s -d%s -s%s %s\n&amp;quot; , $3,$4,$6,$7,$1}' /etc/passwd Ovviamente l&amp;rsquo;output puo&amp;rsquo; essere comodamente filtrato con grep, usato via copy&amp;amp;paste, inserito in uno script, eccetera&amp;hellip;</description></item><item><title>gestire i led delle schede PC Engines ALIX in Ruby</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/gestire-i-led-delle-schede-pc-engines-alix/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/gestire-i-led-delle-schede-pc-engines-alix/</guid><description>Natale si avvicina: mentre smanettavo su queste ottime PC Engines ALIX su cui ho installato una Debian modificata, ho scritto una comoda interfaccia per accendere/spegnere e far lampeggiare i led alla velocita&amp;rsquo; desiderata&amp;hellip;
class Led #numero da 1 a 3 def initialize(ledno) ledno++ # passo 0 ma comando 1 ledno=1 if ledno&amp;lt;1 ledno=3 if ledno&amp;gt;3 @ledsyspath=&amp;#34;/sys/devices/platform/leds_alix2/leds/alix:#{ledno}/&amp;#34; end def blink(millisec) File.open(@ledsyspath+&amp;#39;trigger&amp;#39;,&amp;#39;w&amp;#39;) { |f| f.write(&amp;#39;timer&amp;#39;) } File.open(@ledsyspath+&amp;#39;delay_off&amp;#39;,&amp;#39;w&amp;#39;) do |f| f.write(millisec.to_s) end File.open(@ledsyspath+&amp;#39;delay_on&amp;#39;,&amp;#39;w&amp;#39;) do |f| f.</description></item><item><title>background tasks in Ruby e linux</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/background-tasks-in-ruby-e-linux/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/background-tasks-in-ruby-e-linux/</guid><description>A volte negli script Ruby ho bisogno di controllare l&amp;rsquo;esecuzione di un comando eseguito in modalita&amp;rsquo; asincrona, ho creato pertanto una classe apposita:
class BackgroundJob def initialize(cmd) @pid = fork do # this code is run in the child process # you can do anything here, like changing current directory or reopening STDOUT exec cmd end end def stop! # kill it (other signals than TERM may be used, depending on the program you want # to kill.</description></item><item><title>Enerduino</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/enerduino/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/enerduino/</guid><description>Cos&amp;rsquo;e&amp;rsquo; Enerduino? Un progetto nato per controllare il consumo di energia nella mia casa. E perche&amp;rsquo; dovrei fare questo tipo di monitoraggio, chiederete voi? Per esempio per capire le mie abitudini di consumo, per valutare offerte biorarie. Oppure solo per capire dove consumo di piu&amp;rsquo; e magari risparmiare un po&amp;rsquo; di energia.
Esistono molti strumenti per poter fare questo tipo di monitoraggio che si possono acquistare su internet. Questa e&amp;rsquo; la mia soluzione fai-da-te, basata sul controller hardware Arduino.</description></item><item><title>Linux Day 2012</title><link>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/linux-day-2012/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ilmanzo.github.io/post/linux-day-2012/</guid><description>Anche quest&amp;rsquo;anno ho avuto il piacere di partecipare al Linux Day, organizzato per Verona presso la sede del LUG Verona in via dei Gelsi a Montorio; Ho tenuto una breve presentazione su un argomento che mi sta a cuore: partecipare attivamente alla comunita&amp;rsquo; del software libero, perche&amp;rsquo; anche se ormai Linux e Il free software hanno una discreta diffusione, la maggior parte degli utenti si limita all&amp;rsquo;utilizzo passivo e anzi spesso si lamenta per la scarsa qualita&amp;rsquo; del software open.</description></item></channel></rss>